well it's wednesday again so time for
another clip
today's clip is from a call earlier last
week
with the business owner who's
implementing the strategy of cold
calling in his business
and he was struggling to understand why
when he tried to cold sell
that is you know get on the phone with
someone through a cold call and try to
sell to them directly
it wasn't working the way he wanted we
went over the concept of the difference
between cold calling
and cold selling here's a clip
i understand what you mean um what i'm
curious to know is i i know you
mentioned you're you're
struggling with cold calling but are you
cold calling or are you cold selling
okay let me explain so cold calling is
simply the process of calling someone
you don't know it's it's calling someone
who's a cold contact someone you've
you've never had a previous touch point
with cold selling on the other hand is a
subset of cold calling where in addition
to calling someone you don't know
you're actually trying to sell them
something so in in the situation you
describe
what you're struggling with is it
specifically called calling or is it is
it code selling
okay yeah that's that that's that's sort
of what i thought um so what i what i'd
suggest is
leaning more towards cold calling than
cold selling now cold selling is
is it's a completely different beast and
i'm fairly certain no one likes
getting cold cold calls that are called
sales whereas people
will frequently enjoy cold calls if they
create value for them so what i mean by
that is
when you're cold calling the fundamental
focus should be to build a relationship
with the person
you're you're you're contacting to
understand them to qualify
them not to sell them you don't want to
sell to them in that first cold call
now there are some rare circumstances
where what you're selling
you know exactly that that person is is
someone who's interested but most most
cases
those are warm calls those are people
have opted in they're part of some list
they have they have they've taken some
action to indicate that they want
to be sold that product which doesn't
make them cold anymore it makes them
warm or you know lukewarm or
however you want to you you want to
classify it but when it comes to cold
calling when you're first reaching out
to a prospect they don't know anything
about you
they don't know what your product is
they don't know what your services they
don't know what your offer is
you don't even know if if they're
qualified to purchase your product or
service
you should not be trying to sell to them
one one fantastic example my
sales coach used to give me was think of
you know when you go out on a date when
you go out for your first date what
would happen if you asked the person to
if you propose to the person you know
you had a great hour two three
hour long date and then all of a sudden
you get down on one knee and propose
right what what would they think yeah
you're right you probably get some
strange looks and
there's a high probability you'll
probably never hear from that person
again
it's a similar experience when you're
trying to cold sell to someone you just
cold called
right you have just introduced yourself
they just became aware of
of who you are before they had an
opportunity to learn more about your
product or your service
you're trying to propose to them you're
trying to get them to give you
their money right which from from a
business perspective is very similar
to you know when when a life partner
says yes now a lot of people don't cover
this but i mean
i don't want to go into too much depth
on it but essentially the reality of the
situation is is it's much harder
to end a business relationship than it
is to end a marriage it's unfortunate
that's how it is
but that's the reality of it right so
when you when you cold call someone and
you're attempting to
sell to them instantly on the phone
you've spoken to them maybe 90 seconds
and you get your pitch in
it's a high chance it's not going to
work because it's not a good experience
because for that customer's perspective
they see you as just chasing the money
they see you as not really focused on on
delivering value and i know there are
some exceptions and there are people out
there that are
exceptionally good at it and there's
specific services and products that
might be a good fit for it
but fundamentally speaking overall cold
calling is about calling someone you've
never spoken to
and building a relationship with them
doing the foundations of that
relationship
rather than trying to sell to them does
that make sense yeah i i understand what
you mean it can it can be very time
consuming but if you focus on shifting
you know cold calls from trying to get a
sale what you'll start to find is people
are going to be more engaged because the
types of conversation you have
you're not going to be rushing to get
them to a point where they say yes or no
to buy your stuff
and then you try and get them on the
phone it's genius people know people can
pick up on it i'm sure you've received
calls and within the first five or ten
seconds ago this guy's going to sell me
something
i'm just not interested right whereas if
you get a call about someone trying to
show interest in you trying trying to
understand hey you know what
i i saw on your website you guys do seo
can you tell me a little bit more
about about that if they start to
qualify themselves if they start to
assess in that cold call is this someone
i need to sell my product or service to
it creates a fundamentally
better experience and the same will
happen if you focus on creating a
similar experience for you
for your potential clients when you cold
call them right so
the objective of a cold call i think the
best objective to have from a cold call
is
to set up another call a a longer call
maybe 15 minutes 20 minutes half an hour
or an hour if
if it's the right fit but that first
call is literally just to validate
qualify is this is this person a
potential customer
if they are a potential customer what
sort of services or products that i have
will they need
and to what extent will the amount of
value i create to them need to be
integrated in their business
what i mean by that is a lot of times
the products or services or what you
offer
need to be customized for that specific
business just a little bit
in that cold call what you want to do is
you want to assess how sophisticated are
they as a customer where do they fall
within the
the the target customers that you have
do they have money to buy your services
you don't want to spend three weeks
going through a sales process with
someone who fundamentally
can't buy from you right so that first
call
is really about just assessing is this
someone i want to build a relationship
with
you want to build relationships with
customers that have money that are
eligible to buy your services right you
don't want to build relationships
with people that are fun that you know
that that's a personal thing that has
nothing to do with your business
right so when you're cold calling what i
would encourage you to do is
focus on really trying to identify and
understand that that customer learn more
about their business
right learn more about if your product
or service is a good fit and if it's not
no harm no foul just you know you can
you can end the call right there be like
you know what i really appreciate you
use uh spending some time to explain
your business um this is what i do i
don't think it's a
it's a right fit give them give them an
opportunity to to say yes or no but
fundamentally most people will
appreciate that most people will enjoy
that because it's so different
from all the other cold selling cold
calls that they get right so
again i suggest focusing on cold calling
rather than coal selling and i'm sure
what you'll you'll start to see is
is a difference in in your motivation
and a difference in the way the
conversations go
does that make sense i hope you found
that clip useful
in the comments below let me know have
you ever heard of the difference between
cold calling and cold selling before
if you're a freelancer or business owner
who's struggling to get
clients predictably in the description
below you'll find a link for a
complimentary one-on-one strategy
session with me
we'll dive deep into what you're trying
to do this year and outline a
step-by-step plan to get you where you
want to be
as always be sure to smash that like
button and subscribe
i release more videos like this every
wednesday